<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Poems and Ballads, 1866</title>
                <author xml:id="ACS">Algernon Charles Swinburne</author>
                <editor role="general" xml:id="BN">Bethany Nowviskie</editor>
                <editor role="technical" xml:id="WG">Wayne Graham</editor>
                <sponsor>Scholars &#x2019;Lab, University of Virginia Library</sponsor>
                <principal>Bethany Nowviskie</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.9">
                    <title>work-in-progress</title>
                    <date when="2012-05-27">21 May 2013</date>
                </edition>
                <respStmt><resp>additional annotations provided by </resp><name xml:id="JJM">Jerome J. McGann and Charles Sligh</name></respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Bethany Nowviskie</authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Made freely available under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons BY-NC-SA 3.0</ref> license.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2012">2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Algernon Charles Swinburne</author>
                        <title>Poems and Ballads.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Edward Moxon and Co.</publisher>
                            <date when="1866">1866</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>University of Virginia</institution>
                        <repository>Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library</repository>
                        <idno>PR5506 .P6 1866b (Copy 1; Robert and Virginia Tunstall Trust Fund.)</idno>
                        <msName>Moxon Corrected Edition (MC)</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <collation>
                                    <formula>8, [2], vii, [1], 344 p. ; 18 cm. (8vo)</formula>
                                </collation>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <bindingDesc><p>Original green cloth, stamped in gold and blind.</p></bindingDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="mu.04">Initial printing, Moxon 1866 with printer’s errors (Not yet collated.
                        Any information re: this volume comes from collations by T. J. Wise and my examination of E). 
                        True MUs reported in libraries of Mark Samuels Lasner and Cecil Lang.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="mc.01">Same edition as MU with errors detected by ACS corrected, 1866. Examined: UVA
                        Special Collections and library of Jerome J. McGann. Edition is fully collated.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="mc.02">Same edition as MU with errors detected by ACS corrected, 1866. Examined: UVA
                        Special Collections and library of Jerome J. McGann. Edition is fully collated.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="mc.03">Same edition as MU with errors detected by ACS corrected, 1866. Property of Bethany Nowviskie. Includes the normal Atalanta in
                        Calydon and Chastelard advertisements but is otherwise largely identical to mc.01 and mc.02, with few variations. Edition is fully collated against known variants. </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="hm.09">Moxon remainders with Hotten title-page inserted. Initially found no variants between
                        UVA Special Collections copy and MC (therefore HMC), but Nowviskie HM copy varies. To disentangle.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="e.08">Emory copy, a potential HMU (Moxon Uncorrected with Hotten’s title page tipped in), later re-bound. 
                        NB variants 1.4 and 146.5 – my only witness so far to those readings.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="hr.05">First Hotten reprint set from MU 1866, with additional errors. Examined: Library of Jerome J. McGann.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ny.07">Carleton/Moxon “Author’s Edition” 1866 (set from MU with spelling
                        Americanized, punctuation regularized, and additional errors). Examined: Alderman Library and
                        Special Collections, UVA. (Americanized spellings in a separate listing.)</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="cw.06">Chatto &amp; Windus (Harper’s) edition, 1904. Examined: Alderman Library, UVA,
                        and Chadwyck-Healey electronic edition.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="sp.14"><hi>The Spectator</hi></witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ow.15"><hi>Once A Week</hi></witness>
                    <witness xml:id="cr.16"><hi>Catalogue of the Royal Academy Exhibition</hi></witness>
                    <witness xml:id="hr.10">Possible Hotten reprint as hr.05 above, with variations. </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="mc.11">Possible initial printing, Moxon 1866, with errors detected by ACS corrected, with variations. </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="hr.12">Possible Hotten reprint as hr.05 above, with variations. </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="hr.13">Possible Hotten reprint as hr.05 above, with variations. </witness>
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Work toward a critical edition, tracing the re-introduction of errors identified and corrected by Swinburne in the 1866 Moxon Corrected edition, into subsequent Hotten, Carleton, and Chatto &amp; Windus texts.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>Page signatures and running headers have not been reproduced.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All variants, accidental and substantive, are encoded here&#x2014;with the exception of Americanized spellings in the New York (Carleton) edition, noted separately.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text><body><div><head>Frontmatter</head>
        <div xml:id="ad.atalanta">
        <!-- <pb n="front1"/> -->
        <p rend="center"><hi rend="large">ATALANTA.</hi>
        </p><p rend="center"><hi rend="sc">by ALGERNON C. SWINBURNE</hi>
        </p><p rend="center">Fcap. 8vo, cloth, 6<emph>s.</emph>
        </p><p rend="center"><hi rend="sc">Edward Moxon &#x0026; Co.</hi><lb/><lb/>
        </p><p rend="center"><hi rend="bold">OPINIONS OF THE PRESS</hi>
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;<hi rend="sc">HE</hi> has produced a dramatic poem which abounds from the first page to the last in the finest constituents of poetry—in imagination, fancy, feeling, sentiment, passion, and knowledge of the human heart and soul, combined with a dominant mastery over every species of verse from the stateliest pomp of epic metre to the fluent sweetness of song.&#x2026; He has something of that creative force which all great poets have had, whether they were Greek, Italian, or English—a native and inborn strength, which scholarship may mould, but can never originate. If, as we are given to understand, Mr. Swinburne is a young writer, we do not hesitate to assert that his volume is extraordinary, not simply for strength and vividness of imagination, but (what is far more remarkable with inexperience) for maturity of power, for completeness of self-control, for absolute mastery over the turbulent forces of adolescent genius.&#x2026; That strange, sad, hopeless mood in which the ancient Greek regarded the mysteries of life and death—that austere setting of the soul against the iron will of Destiny which is so full of an immense dignity and pathos—that divinely sorrowful despair of things which can suffer to the miserable end, and sees no after-compensation, and yet goes down to death in majesty, and beauty, and power—these characteristics of the old Greek faith, or want of faith, or whatsoever we may call it, are reflected by Mr. Swinburne with amazing truth and discrimination. There are passages in his poem which seem to wring from the very roots of human ex- perience the sharpest extract of our griefs.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">London Review</hi>, 8<hi>th April</hi>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;Mr. Swinburne has judged well in his choice of a subject. The legend of Calydon is one of the most beautiful in the whole compass of the Greek mythology; fresh, simple, romantic, solemn and pathetic, yet without any of those horrors which shock us in the stories of Thebes or Argos—no Jocasta, no Thyestes, but figures full of heroic truth and nobleness, standing out in the clear bright light of the early morning of Greece.&#x2026; A careful study of the Attic dramatists has enabled him to catch their manner, and to reproduce felicitously many of their terms of expression. The scholar is  
        <!--<pb n="front2"/>-->
        struck, every few lines, by some phrase which he can fancy a direct translation from the Greek, while yet it is in its place both forcible and unaffected. The matter, although not really Greek in its essence, is thrown with great cleverness into a mould which almost beguiles us into forgetting the author, and imagining that we are listening to one of the contemporaries of Euripides who sought to copy the manner of Æschylus.&#x2026; He is, indeed, never more happy than in painting nature, knowing and loving her well, and inspired by her beauty into a vivid force and fulness of expression.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Saturday Review</hi>, 6<emph>th May</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The passion of Althæa is much the finest part of the play. The naturalism of maternal instinct struggling with the feeling of what is due to the shade of her mother and her brothers, goes far beyond the struggle in Antigone or Orestes. Out of many noble passages depicting this feeling we choose the last and most passionate—passionate beyond the limits of Greek passion, and too little ingrained with the Greek awe,—but still exceedingly fine.&#x201D;— <hi rend="sc">Spectator</hi>, <emph>April</emph> 15<emph>th,</emph> 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;He is gifted with no small portion of the all-important Divine fire, without which no man can hope to achieve poetic success; he possesses considerable powers of description, a keen eye for natural scenery, and a copious vocabulary of rich yet simple English.&#x2026; We must now part from our author with cordial congratulations on the success with which he has achieved so difficult a task.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Times</hi>, <emph>June</emph> 6<emph>th</emph>, 1865. 
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;&#x2018;Atalanta in Calydon&#x2019; is the work of a poet.&#x2026; Let our readers say whether they often meet with pictures lovelier in themselves or more truly Greek than those in the following invocation to Artemis;&#x2026; Many strains equal to the above in force, beauty and rhythmical flow might be cited from the chorus. Those which set forth the brevity of man's life, and the darkness which enfolds it, though almost irreverent in their impeachment of the gods, are singularly fine in expression.&#x2026; We yet know not to what poet since Keats we could turn for a representation at once so large in its design and so graphic in its particulars. In the noble hyperbole of description which raises the boar into the veritable scourge of Artemis, there is imagination of the highest kind.&#x2026; A subject for many a painter to come—a grand word-picture, in which the influence of no contemporary can be traced.&#x2026; In the fervour and beauty of his best passages we find no reflection of any modern writer.&#x2026; We must not close without a reference to the Greek lines, plaintive and full of classic grace, which the writer has prefixed to his work in honour of Walter Savage Landor.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Athenæum</hi>, <emph>April</emph> 1<emph>st</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The choruses are so good, that it is difficult to praise them enough. Were our space unlimited, we would transfer them without abridgement to our columns; as it is not, we can only give a few extracts; but we may fairly assume that every one who cares for poetry of a truly high order will make himself familiar with Mr. Swinburne's drama.&#x2026; As we listen to them they seem to set themselves to a strange but grand music, which lingers long on the ear. … Sometimes we are reminded of Shelley in the lyric passages, but it is more the movement of the verse and its wonderful music, than anything else which suggest a resemblance. …
        <!-- <pb n="front3"/> -->
        Mr. Swinburne has lived with the great Athenian dramatists till his tone of thought has somewhat assimilated to theirs, but he has learnt rather to sympathise with them as a contemporary artist, than to copy them as a modern student.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Reader</hi>, <emph>April</emph> 2<emph>2nd</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;Our extracts have shown that we much prefer to let Mr. Swinburne present his own marvellous earnestness and rich delivery of manner than to essay in this, our necessarily brief review, a lengthened criticism or analysis of such a remarkable work of promise.  Apart from the serious endeavour and high devoir to which he has devoted himself in his first appeal to public attention, we would remark the sensuousness, brilliancy, and fervour of the lyrics, which here and there relieve the more sombre and sterner phases of the poem.&#x2026; Assuredly this is the choicest and most complete effort which has for a long time announced that a scholar and a poet has come amongst us.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Morning Herald</hi>, <emph>April</emph> 22<emph>nd,</emph> 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;One grave error, which Mr. Swinburne has almost entirely avoided, is the use of thoughts or expressions which, current now, would be out of place in a tragedy of Greece. He has, with rare artistic feeling, let scarcely a trace appear of modern life. The Poem is all alive with the life of a classic past.&#x2026; The whole play is instinct with power of varied kinds.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Examiner</hi>, <emph>July</emph> 15<emph>th,</emph> 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;We have before said Mr. Swinburne is a subtle analyst of human motive, and possesses great tragic power. The present work shows him to have imagination of the highest order, wonderful play of fancy, and a complete command over every form of versification.&#x2026; He has command of imagery as great as his control of language. He has power which rises to sublimity; passion which deepens into terror; daring which soars beyond reach or control.&#x2026; We have said enough to convince our readers that we regard this poem as a worthy companion to Chastelard, and look upon its author as permanently enrolled among our great English poets.&#x201D;— <hi rend="sc">Sunday Times</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 31<emph>st</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;These lines are marked by that melancholy that always characterises the poetry in proportion to the absence of faith.&#x2026; Could he have faith, of which there is not a trace throughout the poem, except the miserable vacuum created by its absence, he might do wonders as a poet.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">The Tablet</hi>, <emph>August</emph> 12<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;As to the tragedy itself, we find in it everything to praise and nothing to censure. It is one of the few really great poems that have been contributed to English literature since the death of Shelley; and it entitles its author, at once, to a place among the great poets of his country.&#x2026; A tragedy, on the Grecian model, which is remarkable for its intense emotional vitality, the richness and reality of its imaginative images, the perfect precision and finish of its construction, and the combined stateliness, severity, and music of its diction.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Albion</hi>, <emph>November</emph> 11<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;Not the least remarkable and interesting pages of this volume are those to which the author has consigned a tribute of veneration to the memory of Walter Savage Landor, in two compositions of Greek elegiac verse. The first
        <!-- <pb n="front4"/> -->
        is a dedication addressed to Landor while living, in the form of a valediction, on the occasion of his last return to Italy; the second, much the longer of the two, an elegy on his death. No one who has felt how the spirit of the Æschylean tragedy breathes through the English poem, will have been surprised to find—rather, every such reader would have been disappointed if he had not found—that Mr. Swinburne's thoughts move with scarcely less ease and freedom on a modern theme (if indeed Landor may be properly said to belong to his own age so much as to that of Pericles and Augustus) in the language and measures of Callinus and Mimmerus than in his native speech. Of the Greek we will only say that it is not that of a Cambridge prize ode, but something much better—even if more open to minute criticism—than the best of such; not in the least like a cento of dainty classical phrases, but the fresh original gushing of a true poetical vein, nourished by a mastery of the foreign language, like that which Landor himself in his Latin poems.&#x2026; It is evidently the produce, not of the tender lyrical faculty which so often waits on sensitive youth and afterwards fades into the light of common day, nor even of the classical culture of which it is itself a signal illustration, but of an affluent and apprehensive genius, which, with ordinary care and fair fortune, will take a foremost place in English literature.&#x2026; His abstinence from all overdrawn conceits is remarkable in a young poet of any time, and his careful avoidance of the shadowy border land of metaphysics and poetry in which so many versifiers of our own day take refuge from the open scrutiny of critical sunlight deserves full praise and recognition.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Edinburgh Review</hi>, <emph>July</emph>, 1865.
        </p></div>
    <div xml:id="ad.chastelard">
        <p rend="center"><hi rend="large">CHASTELARD.</hi>
        </p><p rend="center"><hi rend="sc">by ALGERNON C. SWINBURNE</hi>
        </p><p rend="center">Fcap. 8vo, cloth, 7<emph>s.</emph>
        </p><p rend="center"><hi rend="sc">Edward Moxon &#x0026; Co.</hi><lb/><lb/>
        </p><p rend="center"><hi rend="bold">OPINIONS OF THE PRESS</hi>
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;<hi rend="sc">The</hi> portraits of Mary and of Chastelard are exaggerated, but only as Michel Angelo's heroic statues are. The consistent, steady madness of Chastelard's passion, which, mad as it is, lies deeper than madness, and, 
        <!--<pb n="front5"/> -->
        wild as it is, burns always without flame, is displayed in a way which is most masterly. As for the Queen, we are quite of opinion that Mr. Swinburne has brought that woman to life again. It will not do, perhaps, to peer closely into her portrait as it lies in these pages: if we do, we become uneasily conscious of blotchy workmanship, with lights too sudden, and shades too deep, and broken harmonies of colour. But close the book, and look at the portrait reflected from it into the mind, and none was ever painted of her so true. It is a portrait which painters and historians alike have only confused; it awaited a poet's hand to this day, and now we have got it. So think we, at any rate ; and in saying so we do not exhaust the praise which is due to the author of&#x201C;Chastelard." The dramatic force of the scenes in the latter half of the poem remains to be applauded, but that luckily for a critic who has come to the end of his tether is a thing which can only be applauded and cannot be described; we give it our homage. But it is very much to the purpose of this article, that just when the poem becomes more dramatic its faults begin to disappear; and before we come to the admirable scene between Mary and Chastelard in prison, we are blinded to whatever remains. The fact seems to be that Mr. Swinburne is less a poet than a dramatist; it is certain that he is capable of writing in a way which entitles him to small consideration as the one, and to great consideration as the other.&#x2026; But in any case it can never be denied that he is a true man of genius.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Pall Mall Gazette</hi>, <emph>April</emph> 27<emph>th</emph>, 1866.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The two principal figures stand out boldly, and on them the poet has bestowed all the riches of his genius.&#x2026; The scene in which having sent for Chastelard, she talks to him in a strange wild mood between love and regretfulness, is extremely subtle and fine.&#x2026; It will not be doubted by any one who has the pulse of poetry in his blood that this is noble writing—writing instinct with the highest spirit of the Elizabethan Muse. And in the speech of Chastelard, when waiting for the Queen in her chamber, we have something of the large, imperial style of Shakespeare himself.&#x2026; The scene between Chastelard and the Queen in prison is also pervaded with the highest inspirations of impassioned poetry; and, though the love-ravings of Chastelard almost pass the bounds commonly permitted to poets, the shadow of fate, lying dark and heavy over all, seems to cool and moderate the glow. In passages such as these, Mr. Swinburne again proves his right to take a permanent stand among our English poets. … Of power, he has abundance; of passion, perhaps more than enough ; of poetry, in its fierce, luminous, and fiery shapes, a wonderful and prodigal richness.&#x2026; Whatever his faults, however, he is a man of genius of the most unmistakable mark. We do not know when it has fallen to the lot of any poet to produce within one year two such plays as &#x2018; Atalanta in Calydon &#x2018; and &#x2018; Chastelard'—dramas conceived and written in two totally distinct styles, and with marked success in both.&#x2026; He has earned a conspicuous name with singular quickness, and we trust that even greater triumphs lie before him in his onward path.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">London Review</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 9<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The choruses in &#x2018;Atalanta &#x2019;were astonishing for their imaginative insight, their richness of imagery, their depth of impassioned thought, the nervous suppleness of their language, and the lyrical flow of their versification; and
        <!-- <pb n="front6"/>-->
        many of the speeches of the characters were full of poetry and dramatic truth. In &#x2018;Chastelard, &#x2019;again, we have a splendid example of the poetry that lies in vehement and absorbing passion; but there is some reason to fear that Mr. Swinburne is wanting in the higher beauty of moral dignity and sweetness.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">London Review</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 30<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;We can only say that it abounds in passages of great poetic merit, and the passion of love is described with all that delicacy and vividness that can only be found in the writings of a poet endowed with extraordinary genius. Mr. Swinburne has well comprehended the character of Mary Stuart, and she is made to stand before the reader a reality, her nature being wonderfully well exhibited. Other characters are represented with marvellous distinctness, and give to the tragedy interest and vitality.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Public Opinion</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 16<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The style is so forcible that there is little that would render the play unfit for the stage, were it not for the great amount of amativeness which the parties have to display before they are disposed of.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Court Circular</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 23<emph>rd</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The picture with which this burst concludes, though too much elaborated, has undeniable grandeur. We could point out passages which, in a dramatic point of view, are yet finer. Those given to Mary Beaton—the only touching character in the play—often reach the height of tragic intensity. Nor is it to be disputed that Mr. Swinburne shows at times a keen insight into the subtleties of human motive, but his chief characters are out of the pale of our sympathy; besides being inherently vicious, the language will offend not only those who have reverence, but those who have taste.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Athenæum</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 23<emph>rd</emph> 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;A tragedy—in which we think he best develops his genius. Once before we said we thought his genius essentially lyric, but he himself has convinced us, not of the contrary, but of the co-existence in him of the dramatic and lyric power.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Court Journal</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 19<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The poem, in fact, is morally repulsive, and all its gilding of fancy and feeling only makes the picture more revolting.&#x2026; The dramatic power, the grace of the beauty of the tragedy, no one can deny.&#x2026; His insight into hidden human motives is marvellously indicated. Altogether, if the poem fails to please, that must be attributed to the subject and the author's mind of it, not to any lack of workmanship of the very highest and most delicate order.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Atlas</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 30<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;It is an unpleasant book, and one by all means to be kept out of the hands of the young and pure-minded, for the licentiousness of many of the images and profanity of not a few of the sentiments are such as happily are not often found in English poets.&#x2026; We cannot doubt that the less sensuous brotherhood of our Northern poets, would join us in denouncing with indignation and disgust such a lamentable prostitution of the English muse.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">John Bull</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 23<emph>rd</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;There are two parts of the play deserving of special praise—the second act, and the closing scenes of the fifth. It is in these and more particularly
        <!-- <pb n=""front7" -->
        in the latter, that Mr. Swinburne displays a combination of dramatic and poetic power beyond what is seen in anything that his pen has yet produced.&#x2026; Were it not for their exquisite elegance of expression, these constant exhibitions of passion would deserve severe reprobation.&#x2026; Regarding the work as a whole, we must thank Mr. Swinburne for a dramatic poem of great power, careful elaboration of plot, artistic disposition of scenes; for admirable descriptions of human emotion and passion; for terse, forcible, yet sweet expression, and a generally scrupulous melody of rhythm.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Reader</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 2<emph>nd</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;Mr. Swinburne has written a tragedy, which not only is one of the most remarkable productions of modern days, but which in originality of conception and boldness of treatment has never been surpassed. The triumph which Mr. Swinburne has achieved in &#x2018;Chastelard &#x2019;is the more noteworthy, since the splendid gifts of which its composition proclaims him the possessor are totally distinct from those which in &#x2018;Atalanta in Calydon, &#x2019;gained him a foremost position among modem poets. In the earlier production, amid all the sublime imagery and lyrical sweetness, the grace truly classic, the boldness of thought and the exquisite charm of versification which constituted it a work of accomplished and all but unrivalled beauty, there was no foreshadowing of the dramatic fire and the weird and almost unholy power which characterise its successor.&#x2026; From this point, where the interest has already reached what appears a climax, each situation is more dramatic and more stirring than the one preceding it. The skill with which—the passions being already at white heat—the action is heightened without anti-climax is absolutely wonderful.&#x2026; The last few words we give in their integrity; no word of ours can add aught to their terrible pathos and dramatic force. With them, and without an added word, we shall conclude our notice of this most remarkable tragedy of modern times.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Sunday Times</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 3<emph>rd</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;Here, in his new poem of&#x201C;Chastelard" is Mr. Algernon Swinburne writing French chansons of which Chastelard himself or Ronsard might have been proud. So good are they that by many they are imagined to be merely quotations, transcripts from the original French author. But there is no doubt they are Mr. Swinburne's own composition. Here are two which are exquisite in taste, feeling, and spirit.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Morning Star</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 25<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;Here and there occur passages which we unhesitatingly affirm are not surpassed in the language.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Liverpool Albion</hi>, <emph>January</emph> 6<emph>th, 1866.</emph>
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The public to which Mr. Swinburne appeals will consist exclusively of those readers who enjoy a work of art for its own sake, and who care more for the power of the representation than for any worth in what is represented.&#x2026; Mr. Swinburne has produced a poem which many may dislike but which none can contemn, which many will lay down unread but which few will read once only. It cannot be called an advance upon &#x2018;Atalanta, &#x2019;for it is something totally different, except in its disregard of conventional proprieties, and its independence of the poetical habits of the day. There is the same richness without tawdriness of language, the same novelty without strangeness of expression, the same continual sense of the indispensable duty of melody in verse, which some of our most pretentious poets
        <!-- <pb n="front8"/> -->
        either forget or disown.&#x2026; The scene in the Queen's chamber is very beautiful, but ingeniously wicked as the rest.&#x2026; For dexterity of fence, both in feeling and language, this scene may rank with the masterpieces of our older drama.&#x2026; The gyrations are so unexpected, and the changes so numerous, that in less masterly hands the effect would be rather that of a psychological puzzle than of a dramatic evolution.&#x2026; It is impossible that this play should not highly raise Mr. Swinburne's reputation. There are artistic defects in it, but not to be mentioned beside the artistic merits. His preface to Moxon's &#x2018;Selections from Byron &#x2019;is another instance of the fact, too often forgotten, that there is no education for the writing of superior prose like the serious practice of poetry; and with this double power, Mr. Swinburne's future career must be an object of much interest to all who estimate aright the worth and weight of British literature in the intellectual and moral history of mankind.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Fortnightly Review</hi>, <emph>April</emph> 15<emph>th</emph>, 1866.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">“He fills out this bold outline, and supplies missing links in the story, and imparts life and form and colour to the whole picture, and reproduces contemporaneous personages and scenery, and, with deep probing of human nature and fine play of imagination, unveils the pathetic tragedy that has so long slept hidden in the dry and trite historic page. The result is a masterpiece of literary art, whether contemplated as to conception of character, ideals of love and heroism, treatment of a grand and moving theme, majesty, beauty, and purity of style, or lesson to the heart and mind.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">The Albion</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 23<emph>rd</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The story is vaguely and ineffectively presented. There is little to relieve the repulsive character of the whole tone of the play. It dwells pertinaciously and too warmly upon scenes which are neither noble, edifying, nor decent.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">Boston Daily Advertiser</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 14<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;We have but re-echoed the judgment of all competent critics, in saying that Swinburne rightfully ranks with the few great poets of this and of other ages. His present work is one of the finest artistic efforts which we have ever chanced to encounter. It has more human interest than his &#x2018;Atalanta in Calydon, &#x2019;while it is couched in the same vigorous and splendid diction, and ‘is richly dight’ with melodious and sweetly magnificent songs.&#x2026; His portraiture is one of the amplest, most thoroughly elaborated, and most gorgeously coloured, in the whole wide range of British poetry.&#x201D;—<hi rend="sc">New York Weekly Review</hi>, <emph>December</emph> 9<emph>th</emph>, 1865.
        </p><p rend="ti-1">&#x201C;The sustained and elastic strength of the fourth act, in which the turns and windings of Mary's will as to Chastelard's death are drawn out—her perplexity, ruthlessness, contempt for a weak man and for a cruel unknightly man, fear of public scorn, remorse for her love, vindictive bitterness against Darnley, all chasing one another over her mind, with the subtlest changes—make one of the most superb scenes for which a drama of character gives room. We feel that the writer is rejoicing in his own skill in unravelling the changeful mysteries of a highly complex character. He exults in his mastery over the Queen's rapid passage from one mood to another, and in the magic by which he can produce and control her Protean transformations.&#x201D;— <hi rend="sc">Saturday Review</hi>, <emph>May</emph> 26<emph>th</emph>, 1866.
        </p></div></div></body></text></TEI>