<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes Regarding Poems and Ballads, 1866</title>
                <author xml:id="JRR">Jerome McGann</author>
                <editor role="general" xml:id="BN">Bethany Nowviskie</editor>
                <editor role="technical" xml:id="WG">Wayne Graham</editor>
                <sponsor>Scholars&#x2019; Lab, University of Virginia Library</sponsor>
                <principal>Bethany Nowviskie</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.9">
                    <title>work-in-progress</title>
                    <date when="2013-05-24">24 May 2013</date>
                </edition>
                <respStmt><resp>additional annotations provided by </resp><name xml:id="JJM">Jerome J. McGann and Charles Sligh</name></respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Bethany Nowviskie</authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Made freely available under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons BY-NC-SA 3.0</ref> license.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2013">2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Jermone J. McGann</author> <author>Charles L. Sligh</author>
                        <title>Explanatory Notes</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
                            <date when="2004">2004</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>University of Virginia</institution>
                        <repository>Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library</repository>
                        <idno>PR5506 .P6 1866b (Copy 1; Robert and Virginia Tunstall Trust Fund.)</idno>
                        <msName>Moxon Corrected Edition (MC)</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    
                </msDesc>
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Work toward a critical edition, tracing the re-introduction of errors identified and corrected by Swinburne in the 1866 Moxon Corrected edition, into subsequent Hotten, Carleton, and Chatto &amp; Windus texts.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>Page signatures and running headers have not been reproduced.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All variants, accidental and substantive, are encoded here&#x2014;with the exception of Americanized spellings in the New York (Carleton) edition, noted separately.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            
        </front>
        <body>
            <!--<pb n='475'/>-->
            <div type="note"><head>A Ballad of Life</head>
            <p>Written in 1862, published in <hi>PBi</hi>. The poem is another pastiche work, in this case a kind of dramatic monologue in that we are to imagine it as having been written by &#x2014;and perhaps, then, here &#x201F;translated&#x201D; from &#x2014;a court poet of Lucrezia Borgia, someone like the Tabaldeo Tebaldei ACS invented as the author of his remarkable &#x201F;Chronicle&#x201D; (see excerpts below)
            <!--<pb n='476'/>-->
            written at the same time as this work. The poem is an Italian canzone and was clearly inspired by ACS&#x2019;s reading of D. G. Rossetti&#x2019;s volume The Early Italian Poets (1861), one of the great works of English verse translation. ACS&#x2019;s fascination with Lucrezia Borgia was fed by his reading of Landor (&#x201F;On Seeing a Hair of Lucretia Borgia&#x201D;), Hugo (<hi>Lucrèce Borgia</hi>), and Dumas (<hi>Crimes Célèbres</hi>).</p></div>
            <div type="note"><head>Laus Veneris</head>
            <p>Written 1863, published in <hi>PBi</hi>. Given ACS&#x2019;s explication of his poem in the Notes on Poems and Reviews, the title, &#x201F;praise of Venus&#x201D; would have to be ironical. Based on the medieval German legend of Venus and Tannh&#x00E4;user, the dramatic monologue is spoken by Tannh&#x00E4;user after he has returned to Venus&#x2019;s H&#x00F6;rselberg following his pilgrimage to Rome to seek absolution from Pope Urban IV (1216-64). The poem is composed in the stanza of Fitzgerald&#x2019;s Rubaiyat, which Rossetti had been enthusiastically promoting since 1860, when he found a copy by accident. Walder (chapter 9) regards the poem as thoroughly Baudelairean and specifically in debt to Baudelaire&#x2019;s pamphlet <hi>Richard Wagner et Tannh&#x00E4;user in Paris</hi> (1861), although ACS asserted in his <hi>Notes on Poems and Reviews</hi> that the poem was finished before he received a copy of the pamphlet from Baudelaire.</p>
                <list>
            <item n="3-133"> Adonis: beloved of Venus, he was slain by a boar. See Ovid&#x2019;s Metamorphoses X. 298ff. for the story.</item>
            <item n="3-195"> for her sake: Helen of Troy</item>
            <item n="3-198"> The queen: Cleopatra</item>
            <item n="3-200"> Semiramis: semilegendary queen of ancient Assyria, infamous for her sexual appetites</item>
            <item n="3-253"> bitter love: the love of Christ</item>
            <item n="3-284"> the Dove: the Christian Holy Ghost</item>
            <item n="3-299"> bay-leaf: the laurel, traditional crown for the poet</item>
            <item n="3-355:3-356"> See Jeremiah 13:23.</item>
            <item n="3-357:3-368"> Compare Baudelaire, &#x201F;Correspondances,&#x201D; 5-14.</item>
            <item n="3-391"> Venus was born from sea-foam, according to legend.</item>
            <item n="3-417"> referring to the legend of the Christian Last Judgment</item>
            <item n="3-425"> A pastiche of a medieval formula for closing a text, it means &#x201F;The Praise of Venus is finished.&#x201D; ACS is clearly using it here ironically, as a satirical comment on social orders dominated by the &#x201F;bitter love&#x201D; of Christianity.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>The Triumph of Time</head>
                <p>The Triumph of Time. Written 1863 or perhaps 1864, published in <hi>PBi</hi>. Although strictly a dramatic monologue, the poem is usually read autobiographically, as ACS&#x2019;s poetical account ot his early disappointment in love. In this reading, AGS&#x2019;s &#x201F;lost love&#x201D; is taken to be his cousin Mary Gordon, who married Col. Robert Disney Leith in 1865. See the commentary on the poem in the <hi>Notes on Poems and Reviews</hi>, where ACS casts it as part of the romantic myth of how a poet comes into his vocation to art &#x2014;a myth of regular resort throughout the nineteenth century and most famously articulated, perhaps, by Shelley; &#x201F;Most wretched men/Are cradled into poetry by wrong, / They learn in suffering what they teach in song&#x201D; Although the title recalls Petrarch&#x2019;s celebrated sequence of <hi>Trionfi</hi>, its most immediate locus of attention is Tennyson&#x2019;s &#x201F;Locksley Hall,&#x201D; as is especially clear from lines 113ff., which recall lines 57-58 in Tennyson&#x2019;s poem. Both tell the story of the &#x201F;triumph&#x201D; of the quotidian world over the speaker&#x2019;s dream of establishing an earthly paradise of love. In ACS the triumph is a pyrrhic one because it results in the speaker&#x2019;s initial turn to the vocation of poetry, of which this very poem appears as the first fruit. Its &#x201F;sick dreams and sad . . . dull delight[s]&#x201D; are the speaker&#x2019;s, not the poem&#x2019;s.</p>
                <list>
                <item n="5-29"> a Eucharistic reference &#x2014; a parodic move recurrent in ACS&#x2019;s work generally</item>
                <item n="5-30"> Genesis 3:5. Biblical allusions appear throughout (see e,g, lines 30,36,102,168,304,363).</item>
                <item n="5-62"> mother: Aphrodite</item>
                <item n="5-83"> According to legend, waves comes in triads, and the third is always the greatest. See Plato, Republic 472a.</item>
                <item n="5-156"> the fates: Clotho, Lachesis, Atropos</item>
                <item n="5-237"> Echoes Hamlet 111.1.</item>
<!--<pb n="477"/>-->
                <item n="5-253"> referencing the Seven Sorrows of the Virgin Mary (see &#x201F;Dolores&#x201D;).</item>
                <item n="5-257:5-320"> This event symbolizes a secular baptism into an imaginative life dedicated to a knowledge of the elemental orders of reality.</item>
                <item n="5-295:5-296"> These are emblems of Christianity for ACS.</item>
                <item n="5-319"> Love: Eros, the boy-god, conventionally pictured with wings</item>
                <item n="5-321-44"> ACS references the legend of the twelith-century troubadour poet Jaufr&#x00E9; Rudel, which is a variation on the Tristan legend. When he was at Oxford ACS wrote a sequence of poems on Rudel and his star-crossed love for the Lady of Tripoli. Rudel figures in Petrarch&#x2019;s &#x201F;Triumph of Love.&#x201D; The &#x201F;midland sea&#x201D; is the Mediterranean.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Itylus</head>
                <p>Itylus. Written in Italy early in 1864; first published <hi>PBi</hi>. The source is Ovid, Metamorphoses VI. 424ff. The poem retails the gruesome story of the rape of Philomela by her brother-in-law King Tereus, married to her sister Procne. Tereus ripped out Philomela&#x2019;s tongue to prevent her from reporting his crime, but she wove a tapestry to reveal it in images. Procne avenged her sister by killing their son Itys and feeding the boy to his unsuspecting father, Tereus. The sisters then fled from Daulis, where the gruesome meal was served. Ovid says Tereus was turned into a hawk while Philomela became a nightingale and her sister a swallow. ACS played many variations on this legend, with its rich resources for exploring the relations of love and poetry and their mar- velous investment in patterns of translation and transformation. In a letter written to Edmund Gosse in 1915, R. W. Raper reported a meeting with ACS in which he said, &#x201F;&#x2018;I don&#x2019;t know whether it has any meaning or not, and I don&#x2019;t care: I am quite sure it is the most musical, and that is what I do care about.&#x2019; He said that alter he had composed it, he went out and chanted it to the nightingales, and they fell into tune.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Anactoria</head>
                <p>Anactoria. First drafted in 1863, the poem was later reworked, perhaps in 1865, when ACS added lines 155-88; first published <hi>PBi</hi>. One of the greatest poems of the nineteenth century, its intense eroticism shocked ACS&#x2019;s contemporaries, and the poem was pointedly denounced by hostile reviewers (see ACS&#x2019;s reply in his <hi>Notes on Poems and Reviews</hi>). ACS rightly pointed out (.Letters II. 74) that its &#x201F;scheme of movement and modulation&#x201D; was &#x201F;original in structure and combination,&#x201D; and he used this scheme as the metrical basis for <hi>Tristram of Lyonesse</hi>. &#x201F;Anactoria&#x201D; is a dramatic monologue addressed by Sappho to her lover Anactoria, whom Sappho berates for her infidelity. The poem is formally a set of &#x201F;variations on a theme&#x201D; established originally by Sappho. That ACS was aware of the musical analogy is apparent from the poem&#x2019;s own variations on the theme of musicality, where the poet&#x2019;s procedural &#x201F;scheme&#x201D; for his work is most clearly on exhibit. The monologue&#x2019;s specific point of departure is the Greek poet&#x2019;s famous (so-called) &#x201F;Ode to Aphrodite,&#x201D; which ACS echoes and recalls, as he does other passages from Sappho&#x2019;s surviving fragmentary corpus. Besides the epigraph, the passages distincdy echoing Sappho are 63,70,73- 74, 81-84,189-200, 203-14. ACS regarded Sappho as the greatest poet who ever lived, and she inspired him to some of his most magnificent verse (see &#x201F;Sapphics&#x201D; and &#x201F;On the Cliffs&#x201D;). The best commentary on the poem&#x2019;s astonishing verbal pyrotechnics is by Lang (<hi>Pre-Raphaelites and their Circle</hi>, 522-24), who also observes that the poem&#x2019;s couplets fall into &#x201F;four grand modula- tions of accelerating intensity (11. 1-58, 59-152, 153-88, 189-304).&#x201D; But neither Lang nor other scholars comment on the crucial set of mirror texts at lines 35-46 and 47-58 (and see below the commentary for <hi>Tristram of Lyonesse</hi>). This (double) passage indexes the central idea pervading the poem: that the poetic imagination has the power to generate infinite transformations and that it is, in this respect, the source and end and test of the ceaseless generative power displayed in the natural world.</p>
                <list>
                <item>Epigraph: The text is emended (by ACS) from a corrupt line in the &#x201F;Ode to Aphrodite.&#x201D; The emendation is the first of ACS&#x2019;s &#x201F;variations.&#x201D; The epigraph translates, &#x201F;From whom by persuasion have you vainly caught love&#x201D; (i.e., who has seduced you to the hopelessness of loving?). 22 Erinna: a Greek poetess from Lesbos mentioned by Sappho, here made one of her lovers; Erotion: a male love (see ACS&#x2019;s poem so titled)</item>
                <item n="9-45"> Aphrodite&#x2019;s girdle, one of her most seductive habiliments</item>
<!--<pb n="478"/>-->
                <item n="9-64"> Paphos: the location of the shrine to Aphrodite on Cyprus</item>
                <item n="9-155:9-188"> This passage has been sharply criticized by many. Early reviewers were appalled at the fierce attack on the sadomasochism of Judaeo-Christian ideology. Others, including later critics, fault the passage on formal grounds, as being out of keeping with Sappho&#x2019;s monologue. But ACS&#x2019;s monologues (like D. G. Rossetti&#x2019;s) are themselves variations on the strict model made famous by Browning. As the supreme type of the poet, Sappho is for ACS &#x201F;now [i.e., in the nineteenth century] no more a singer, but a song&#x201D; (&#x201F;Thalassius&#x201D; 474). In this sense, which is essential to ACS&#x2019;s argument, Sappho here becomes &#x201F;one with&#x201D; ACS and one with Anactoria (and with &#x201F;Anactoria&#x201D;): &#x201F;one with all these things, / With all high things for ever&#x201D; (276-77). That is the argument demonstrated in the poem&#x2019;s concluding section (see especially lines 243-304).</item>
                <item n="9-260:9-265"> glancing at the legend that Sappho died in a fit of love-despair by hurling herself into the sea from a cliff in Leucadia</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Hymn to Proserpine</head>
                <p>Hymn to Proserpine. ACS read the poem to William Bell Scott in December 1862; first published <hi>PBi</hi>. It is a dramatic monologue, what ACS called &#x201F;the deathsong of spiritual decadence&#x201D; spoken by a pagan believer living after the establishment of Christianity as the official religion of Rome in 379-85 by the emperor Theodosius. The poem&#x2019;s epigraph is the famous remark attributed to Julian, emperor from 361 to 363 and called the Apostate because he rejected the Christian faith that was coming to power in Rome. The source is Theodoret&#x2019;s <hi>Ecclesiastical History</hi> 3.20. The poem is largely governed by the contrast between the pagan queen, worshipped under various names (Proserpine, Venus, Cybele), and the Queen of Heaven of the Christians, the Blessed Virgin, called here a &#x201F;slave among slaves&#x201D; (85) in allusion to her son Jesus (&#x201F;despised and rejected&#x201D;), sometimes called (like his vicar on earth, the pope) the &#x201F;servant of servants.&#x201D; Invoking a Nietzschean myth of &#x201F;eternal return&#x201D; (see line 46), the poem implicitly comments on contemporary Christianity&#x2019;s &#x201F;spiritual decadence.&#x201D; The famous couplet (35-36) marks Christianity as a religion that makes death and forgetfulness (&#x201F;things Lethean&#x201D;) the hallmarks of its living faith. Christianity works to forget its pagan inheritance, and it represents &#x201F;the fullness of death&#x201D; because it seeks to turn the brief space of a human life into a morbid experience. The speaker&#x2019;s pagan faith, by contrast, marks the death of the body as an unambiguous blessing given to men and women after the initial &#x2014; ambiguous and testing &#x2014;gift of life. ACS&#x2019;s poem may be usefully compared with D. G. Rossetti&#x2019;s &#x201F;The Burden of Nineveh,&#x201D; which makes its contemporary application in more specific terms.</p>
                <list>
                <item n="10-71"> thy lords: i.e., the Romans, who ruled the world</item>
                <item n="10-80"> Venus was the mother of Aeneas, who founded Rome.</item>
                <item n="10-108"> The line echoes a famous remark by the Roman philosopher Epictetus (ca. A.D. 60-120): Thou art a little soul bearing up a corpse.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Hermaphroditus</head>
                <p>Composed March 1863, published <hi>PBi</hi>. The four sonnets (Italian in form) construct an interpretation of the Hellenistic sculpture of the sleeping Hermaphrodite in the Louvre (see ACS&#x2019;s note to the poem). Ovid is the source of the legend (Metamorphoses IV 285- 388): that when the beautiful youth Hermaphroditus rejected the love of the nymph Salmacis, the gods answered her prayer that the two be joined by causing him to melt into her when he was swimming in her pool. While the androgyne is an ancient figure of human perfection, in the nineteenth century this union of oppositcs acquired a distinctly erotic character. The key texts impinging on ACS are Henri De Latouche&#x2019;s notorious novel Fragoletta (1829), Balzac&#x2019;s S&#x00E9;raphita and La fille aux yeux d&#x2019;or (both 1835), Gautier&#x2019;s Mademoiselle de Maupin (1836) and Baudelaire&#x2019;s &#x201F;Le Bijoux.&#x201D; See ACS&#x2019;s commentary on his sonnets in Notes on Poems and Reviews, in which he cites Shelley&#x2019;s &#x201F;The Witch of Atlas,&#x201D; which features a hermaphrodite as the familiar spirit of the witch, who represents the power of the imagination. ACS&#x2019;s poem &#x201F;Fragoletta&#x201D; was printed in <hi>PBi</hi> immediately after this work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Anima Anceps</head>
                <p>Composition date is unknown: first published <hi>PBi</hi>. The poem is a carpe diem response to the &#x201F;divided soul&#x201D; of the Latin title, which ACS seems to have lifted from a passage
                <!--<pb n="479"/>-->
                    in Hugo&#x2019;s Notre-Dame de Paris (book VIII, chap. 6). In Hugo the Latin formula is a priestly prayer for a person being sent to execution &#x2014; death presumably ending the soul&#x2019;s self-division. Obviously ACS argues that the divided soul should look for psychic healing not in death but in life. Although the poem inevitably recalls Arthur Clough&#x2019;s &#x201F;Dipsychus,&#x201D; which ACS knew and admired, Byron&#x2019;s splendid &#x201F;Stanzas. &#x2018;Could love for ever&#x2019;&#x201D; is clearly the most important source text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>A Match</head>
                <p>Composed 1862, first published <hi>PBi</hi>. The poem lays out a series of six &#x201F;matches,&#x201D; each introducing a way of defining a possible relation between the lover, who speaks the poem, and his beloved. These matches, conventional antitheses, introduce six sets of assertions that &#x201F;would&#x201D; be the outcome of these hypotheses. The poem is notable, however, for not organizing its six units as anything but an aggregate &#x2014; the order of the stanzas scarcely matters so that ACS short circuits any &#x201F;sense of an ending&#x201D; for his poem. The effect is to make the text a demonstration of the lover / poet&#x2019;s imaginative powers, as if any type of relation between him and his lover would suffice, as if any type of relation would be both possible and desirable.</p></div>
            <div type="note"><head>Faustine</head>
                <p>Probably composed in 1862, first published in The Spectator (31 May 1862) and collected in <hi>PBi</hi>. The best gloss on this astonishing tour de force is still ACS&#x2019;s own comments in his Notes on Poems and Reviews, where &#x201F;the elder Faustina&#x201D; is identified as the poet&#x2019;s inspiration. Around A.D. 110 she married Antoninus Pius, who later (A.D. 137) became emperor. Like her daughter (also named Annia Galena Faustina), the elder Faustina became, perhaps unfairly, a byword for a libidinous, epicene woman.</p>
                <list>
                <item n="21-01">Epigraph &#x201F;Hail, Empress Faustina, they who are about to die salute you&#x201D; (the Roman gladiators&#x2019; traditional salutation before their circus combats). The impish comic overtone of this epigraph emerges to view when we see that the word &#x201F;Faustina&#x201D; here refers not so much to the Roman empress as to ACS&#x2019;s poem and its titular, highly transformational central figure.</item>
                <item n="21-121"> lesbian love (sec &#x201F;Sapphics&#x201D;)</item>
                <item n="21-146"> Priapus, god of gardens and fertility, was born in Lampsacus in Asia Minor.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Stage Love</head>
                <p>Date of composition uncertain, but the poem has a clear connection to &#x201F;A Match,&#x201D; which was written in 1862. First published <hi>PBi</hi>. ACS writes the poem to complicate and explore the traditional contrast between &#x201F;real&#x201D; and &#x201F;stage&#x201D; love, which here figure the relation of any artistic action to its representations. The argument presents the consequences of a real love relationship being undertaken under the auspices of a stage model. As such, the poem distinctly recalls works like Laclos&#x2019;s Les liaisons dangerouses or various works by Gautier, not least of all Mademoiselle de Maupin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>The Leper</head>
                <p>The earliest version of this poem, titled &#x201F;A Vigil&#x201D; was written in 1862; when ACS revised it to the form of its (initial) publication in <hi>PBi</hi> is uncertain, but he is known to have recited it at Fryston in the summer of 1862. The French endnote that ACS gives as the story&#x2019;s source is of course his invention and was translated by Lang as follows: &#x201F;At that time there was in this country a large number of lepers, which greatly displeased the king, since because of them God must have been grievously angered. Now it happened that a noble damsel named Yolande de Salli&#x00E8;res, being afflicted and utterly ravaged by this evil malady, all her friends and relatives, having before their eyes the fear of God, drove her out of their houses and never were willing to receive a thing accursed by God and stinking and abominable to all men. That Lady had been very beautiful and of graceful figure, goodly in stature and lascivious in her life. However, none of her lovers who had ever embraced and kissed her very tenderly was willing to harbor any longer so ugly a woman and so detestable a sinner. Only a clerk who had been at first her servant and go-between in matters of love took her with him and hid her in a small hut. There the wicked woman died an evil death in great misery. And after she died the clerk aforesaid, who out of his great love had for six months, cared for her, washed her, dressed and undressed her every day with his own hands. People even say that this wicked man and cursed clerk, remembering this woman&#x2019;s former great beauty, [now] ravaged, often delighted in kissing her foul and leprous
                <!--<pb n="480"/>-->
                    mouth and in caressing her gently with his loving hands. Therefore, he died of this same abominable disease. This happened near Fontainbellant in Gastenois. And when King Philip heard the story he marveled greatly.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Lang&#x2019;s notes and commentary on the ballad will probably never be surpassed. They expose what he calls the poem&#x2019;s &#x201F;functional ambiguities,&#x201D; &#x201F;all part of a conspiracy luring the willing reader to interpretations that can neither be wholly sustained nor comfortably dismissed&#x201D;. He cites line 137 as a &#x201F;safe&#x201D; example of such ambiguities (it &#x201F;may or may not suggest that the clerk &#x2018;died of this same abominable disease&#x2019;&#x201D;) and line 12 as one with &#x201F;other reverberations&#x201D; than the most obvious one (see Lang, The Pre-Raphaelites and their Circle, 521-22). The poem should be compared with ACS&#x2019;s story &#x201F;Dead Love.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Before the Mirror</head>
                <p>A rare case of a poem which can be dated exactly. Composed 2 April 1865, published <hi>PBi</hi> (but ACS published stanzas 4 and 6 in the Royal Society Exhibition Catalogue (1865) to accompany James Whistler&#x2019;s picture The Little White Girl, which inspired the poem). When ACS sent Whistler a copy of the poem in a letter (letters I. 118-20), he told him that he &#x201F;brought [it] off at once.&#x201D; But an early manuscript (late 1850s) titled &#x201F;The Dreamer&#x201D; comprises a version of the last three stanzas plus a fourth (unpublished) stanza that comes third in this poem (and that would have been &#x201F;Before the Mirror&#x201D;&#x2019;s penultimate stanza). Its relevance to the received poem is clear:</p>
            <lg>
                <l>A painted dream, beholden,</l>
                <l rend="ti-1">Of no man&#x2019;s eye,</l>
                <l>Framed in far memories, golden</l>
                <l rend="ti-1">As hope when nigh</l>
                <l>Holds fast her soul that hears</l>
                <l>Faint waters flow like tears</l>
                <l>By shores no sunbeam cheers</l>
                <l rend="ti-1">From all the sky.</l>
            </lg>
                <p>Whistler&#x2019;s painting led ACS to work his early lines into an artistic expression of the function of art as a second-order phantasm (or &#x201F;dream&#x201D;) constructed to expose the phantasms that organize so much of our ordinary worlds. As he wrote to Whistler, &#x201F;I found . . . the notion of sad and glad mystery in the face languidly contemplative of its own phantom and all other things seen by their phantoms.&#x201D;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Dolores</head>
                <p>Composed in the spring and perhaps the summer, 1865; published <hi>PBi</hi>. The outrage of ACS&#x2019;s early reviewers at this poem has rarely been taken as seriously as it should. The poem <hi>is</hi> outrageous, consciously so, and is best read as the &#x201F;parody&#x201D; that Lafourcade long since declared it to be. Indeed, the poem&#x2019;s splendor falls from its deliberately ludic approach to its materials: not just to its Christian materials, but to its Sadean inversions as well. The poem&#x2019;s corrosive power rests in its implicit argument that the Christian and the Sadean economies are codependent functions of each other. The poem is a triumph of the comic spirit over what Blake called &#x201F;the wastes of moral law.&#x201D; ACS&#x2019;s high-spirited letter to Charles Augustus Howell (May or June 1865) provides the best gloss the poem has ever had: &#x201F;I have added four more jets of boiling and poisonous infamy to the perennial and poisonous fountain of Dolores,&#x201D; and he adds a PS to the letter with a sample, lines 173-80. A second PS immediately follows: &#x201F;Since writing the above I have added ten verses to D. &#x2014;très infâmes et très bien tourn&#x00E9;s. &#x2018;Oh! Monsieur &#x2014; peut-on prendre du plaisir à telles horreurs? Tu le vois, Justine, je bande-oh! Putain, que tu vas souffrir&#x2019; &#x2014;.&#x201D;</p>
                <p>Walder (chapter 13) and Haynes both supply a thorough account of ACS&#x2019;s many sources: from the Bible, the Book of Common Prayer, and the Roman Missal to Sade, Byron, Gautier, and Baudelaire. ACS&#x2019;s subtitle gives the French form of Our Lady of Sorrows, one of the appellations of the Virgin Mary (whose &#x201F;mysteries&#x201D; &#x2014; Joyful, Sorrowful, and Glorious &#x2014;all get celebrated in the &#x201F;Litanies&#x201D; to her that provide the basis for ACS&#x2019;s bravura exercise).</p>
                <list>
                <item n="36-19"> &#x201F;Tower of ivory&#x201D; (see the Song of Songs 7: 4) and &#x201F;mystical rose&#x201D; are two appellations of the Virgin Mary in one of her litanies.</item>
                <item n="36-21"> &#x201F;Tower of ivory&#x201D; (see the Song of Songs 7: 4) and &#x201F;mystical rose&#x201D; are two appellations of the Virgin Mary in one of her litanies.</item>
                <!--<pb n="481"/>-->
                <item n="36-51"> Libitina: ancient Italian goddess of death and fertility; Priapus: god of sexual potency</item>
<item n="36-217:36-256"> an evocation of the bloodthirsty spectacles of ancicnt Rome, culminating (249f4.) in an allusion to the legend that Nero set fire to Rome in A.D.64</item>
<item n="36-223"> Thalassa, one of Aphrodite&#x2019;s names, meaning &#x201F;sea-born&#x201D;</item>
<item n="36-228"> children of change: Christians</item>
<item n="36-231"> one: Nero</item>
<item n="36-281"> Vesta: goddess of the hearth</item>
<item n="36-299"> Alciphron: Greek poet and rhetorician (second century), famous for his &#x201F;imaginary letters&#x201D; supposed to have been written by persons of an earlier age. Arisbe: in this instance ACS must be thinking of the Lesbian Arisbe, daughter of Macar.</item>
<item n="36-340"> Catullus: the great Roman poet (87-54 B.C.); see below, &#x201F;Hendecasyllabics&#x201D;)</item>
<item n="36-371"> Exodus 7: 8-10</item>
<item n="36-375"> prophet: the Marquis de Sade</item>
<item n="36-406"> Aphaca: in Asia Minor, a center for worship of Venus and Priapus</item>
<item n="36-409:36--410"> three of Aphrodite&#x2019;s names</item>
<item n="36-438"> tares: see Matthew 13: 25-40</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>The Garden of Proserpine</head>
                <p>The Garden of Proserpine. The date of composition is uncertain, but 1865 is perhaps not unreasonable; first published in <hi>PBi</hi>. Some years after the publication of <hi>PBi</hi>, ACS told a dinner party that this piece, &#x201F;The Triumph of Time,&#x201D; and &#x201F;Dolores&#x201D; were related to each other and were &#x201F;beyond all the rest [of the poems in <hi>PBi</hi>] autobiographical.&#x201D; According to this tale, after a period of sensual indulgence &#x201F;with which he had sought relief&#x201D; from the trauma of his &#x201F;lost love,&#x201D; he came to Proserpine&#x2019;s garden &#x201F;to find ... a haven of undisturbed rest.&#x201D; Whatever the historical truth of this tale, the poem certainly, and exquisitely, identifies that &#x201F;haven&#x201D; with poetry itself. Standing behind the poem is a general allusion to one of ACS&#x2019;s favorite New Testament passages, Galatians 6:7-9, which of course is here translated into a secular humanist meaning. This flagrantly symbolic poem should be compared (and contrasted) with &#x201F;A Forsaken Garden,&#x201D; in which the illusory stabilities of the natural world are exposed by a consummate artifice.</p>
                <p>Title ACS leaves it ambiguous whether the garden references the legendary place in the upper world where Proserpine (Kore) was raped away by Hades while she was gathering &#x201F;bloomless buds of poppies&#x201D; (27) or the garden in the underworld where she ate the pomegranate from Hades&#x2019; garden. The literary sources locate the upper world garden with many different places in the ancient world, Sicilian Enna and Attic Elcusis being the most common.</p>
                <list>
                <item n="37-70:37:72"> recalls the opening of Shelley&#x2019;s &#x201F;Ode to the West Wind&#x201D;</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Hendecasyllabics</head>
                <p>Composed 1865, first published <hi>PBi</hi>. A homage to Catullus, the poem specifically recalls Carmen XLVI, which is cast as a celebration of spring in the classical form of hendecasyllablcs. ACS&#x2019;s poem inverts and transforms Catullus in order to celebrate not nature but art and imagination. Like its companion &#x201F;Sapphics&#x201D; this poem is therefore far more than a formal imitation of or response to Catullus, whom ACS regarded as one of the three supreme masters of lyric verse in Western literature (after Sappho and on a par with Shelley). The inversion of Catullus is the framework for a whole set of related transformations. Particularly notable is the inverted echo of Milton (&#x201F;Lycidas&#x201D; 26) in line 6 and of the Song of Songs (2:11-13) at lines 19-25. The poem announces an entrance into the same world figured in &#x201F;The Garden of Proserpine&#x201D; and its nonnatural flowers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="note"><head>Sapphics</head>
                <p>The date of composition is uncertain, but the poem&#x2019;s close relation to &#x201F;Anactoria&#x201D; suggests a date of 1863; first published <hi>PBi</hi>. As &#x201F;Hendecasyllabics&#x201D; reworked Catullus&#x2019;s Carmen XLVI into a myth of poetry, this poem reworks Sappho&#x2019;s &#x201F;Ode to Aphrodite&#x201D; in an even more spectacular way. The poem tells a story of how Sappho assumed her office and fame as &#x201F;the tenth muse&#x201D;: by repudiating Aphrodite and the order of natural love and devoting herself to the order of impossible things. Sappho was from Mitylene, on Lesbos.</p></div>
            <div type="note">
                <!--<pb n="482"/>-->
                <head>Dedication, 1865</head>
                <p>Composed 1865, first published <hi>PBi</hi>, the concluding poem of the volume. The poem is addressed to Edward Burne Jones (later Burne-Jones), the painter. They met at Oxford and remained lifelong friends. The poem deliberately recapitulates the motifs and images that recur throughout <hi>PBi</hi> in order to make clear that all are in the end poetic transformations &#x2014; literally, literal figures of the power of poetic imagination.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>