<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Title</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <note target="#1">
          <p>
          A Ballad of Life. Written in 1862, published in PBi. The poem is another pastiche work, in this
          case a kind of dramatic monologue in that we are to imagine it as having been written by —and
          perhaps, then, here "translated" from —a court poet of Lucrezia Borgia, someone like the Ta-
          baldeo Tebaldei ACS invented as the author of his remarkable "Chronicle" (see excerpts below)
          written at the same time as this work. The poem is an Italian canzone and was clearly inspired
          by ACS's reading of D. G. Rossetti's volume The Early Italian Poets (1861), one of the great works
          of English verse translation. ACS's fascination with Lucrezia Borgia was fed by his reading of
          Landor ("On Seeing a Hair of Lucretia Borgia"), Hugo (Lucrèce Borgia), and Dumas (Crimes
          Célèbres).
          </p>
        </note>
        
        <note target="#3">
          <p>
            Laus Veneris. Written 1863, published in PBi. Given ACS's explication of his poem in the Notes
            on Poems and Reviews, the title, "praise of Venus" would have to be ironical. Based on the me-
            dieval German legend of Venus and Tannhauser, the dramatic monologue is spoken by
            Tannhauser after he has returned to Venus's Horselberg following his pilgrimage to Rome to
            seek absolution from Pope Urban IV (1216-64). The poem is composed in the stanza of Fitzger-
            ald's Rubaiyat, which Rossetti had been enthusiastically promoting since i860, when he found
            a copy by accident. Walder (chapter 9) regards the poem as thoroughly Baudelaircan and speci-
            fically in debt to Baudelaire's pamphlet Richard Wagner et Tannhauser in Paris (1861), although
            ACS asserted in his Notes on Poems and Reviews that the poem was finished before he received a
            copy of the pamphlet from Baudelaire.
          </p>
          <list>
            <item n="3-133">133 Adonis: beloved of Venus, he was slain by a boar. See Ovid's Metamorphoses X. 298ff. for the story</item>
            <item n="3-195">195 for her sake: Helen of Troy</item>
            <item n="3-198">198 The queen: Cleopatra</item>
            <item n="3-200">200 Semiramis: semilegendary queen of ancient Assyria, infamous for her sexual appetites</item>
            <item n="3-253">253 bitter love: the love of Christ</item>
            <item n="3-198">284 the Dove: the Christian Holy Ghost</item>
            <item n="3-299">299 bay-leaf: the laurel, traditional crown for the poet</item>
            <item n="3-355:3-356">355-56 See Jeremiah 13:23.</item>
            <item n="3-357:3-368">357 - 68 Compare Baudelaire, "Correspondances," 5-14.</item>
            <item n="3-391">391 Venus was born from sea-foam, according to legend.</item>
            <item n="3-417">417 referring to the legend of the Christian Last Judgment</item>
            <item n="3-425">425 A pastiche of a medieval formula for closing a text, it means "The Praise of Venus is
              finished." ACS is clearly using it here ironically, as a satirical comment on social orders domi-
              nated by the "bitter love" of Christianity.</item>
          </list>
        </note>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>