<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Poems and Ballads, 1866</title>
                <author xml:id="ACS">Algernon Charles Swinburne</author>
                <editor role="general" xml:id="BN">Bethany Nowviskie</editor>
                <editor role="technical" xml:id="WG">Wayne Graham</editor>
                <sponsor>Scholars' Lab, University of Virginia Library</sponsor>
                <principal>Bethany Nowviskie</principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.9">
                    <title>work-in-progress</title>
                    <date when="2012-05-27">21 May 2013</date>
                </edition>
                <respStmt><resp>additional annotations provided by </resp><name xml:id="JJM">Jerome J. McGann and Charles Sligh</name></respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Bethany Nowviskie</authority>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Made freely available under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons BY-NC-SA 3.0</ref> license.</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2012">2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Algernon Charles Swinburne</author>
                        <title>Poems and Ballads.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Edward Moxon and Co.</publisher>
                            <date when="1866">1866</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>University of Virginia</institution>
                        <repository>Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library</repository>
                        <idno>PR5506 .P6 1866b (Copy 1; Robert and Virginia Tunstall Trust Fund.)</idno>
                        <msName>Moxon Corrected Edition (MC)</msName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <collation>
                                    <formula>8, [2], vii, [1], 344 p. ; 18 cm. (8vo)</formula>
                                </collation>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <bindingDesc><p>Original green cloth, stamped in gold and blind.</p></bindingDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="mu">Initial printing, Moxon 1866 with printer’s errors (Not yet collated.
                        Any information re: this volume comes from collations by T. J. Wise and my examination of E). 
                        True MUs reported in libraries of Mark Samuels Lasner and Cecil Lang.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="mc">Same edition as MU with errors detected by ACS corrected, 1866. Examined: UVA
                        Special Collections and library of Jerome J. McGann. </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="hm">Moxon remainders with Hotten title-page inserted. Initially found no variants between
                        UVA Special Collections copy and MC (therefore HMC), but Nowviskie HM copy varies. To disentangle.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="e">Emory copy, a potential HMU (Moxon Uncorrected with Hotten’s title page tipped in), later re-bound. 
                        NB variants 1.4 and 146.5 – my only witness so far to those readings.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="hr">First Hotten reprint set from MU 1866, with additional errors. Examined: Library of Jerome J. McGann.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ny">Carleton/Moxon “Author’s Edition” 1866 (set from MU with spelling
                        Americanized, punctuation regularized, and additional errors). Examined: Alderman Library and
                        Special Collections, UVA. (Americanized spellings in a separate listing.)</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="cw">Chatto &amp; Windus (Harper’s) edition, 1904. Examined: Alderman Library, UVA,
                        and Chadwyck-Healey electronic edition.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="sp"><hi>The <emph>Spectator</emph></hi></witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ow"><hi>Once A Week</hi></witness>
                    <witness xml:id="cr"><hi>Catalogue of the Royal Academy Exhibition</hi></witness>
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Work toward a critical edition, tracing the re-introduction of errors identified and corrected by Swinburne in the 1866 Moxon Corrected edition, into subsequent Hotten, Carleton, and Chatto &amp; Windus texts.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>Page signatures and running headers have not been reproduced.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All variants, accidental and substantive, are encoded here&#x2014;with the exception of Americanized spellings in the New York (Carleton) edition, noted separately.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <gap>
                <desc>All front matter (including advertisements, half title, title, dedication, and table of contents) has been temporarily omitted.</desc>
            </gap>
        </front>
        <body>
            <!-- notes:
                    - do we want links from works mentioned in the timeline to the relevant text?-->
            <div><head>Publication History</head>
                <div><head>1860</head>
                <p><date when="18601200">Dec.</date><lb/>
                    Publication of two verse-plays, <hi>The Queen Mother</hi> and <hi>Rosamond</hi>, by Basil Montague Pickering. Immediately withdrawn and re-issued by Edward Moxon and Co.</p></div>
                <div><head>1862</head>
                <p><date when="18620412">Apr. 12</date><lb/><!-- double-check this date? - tm -->
                    “Victor Hugo’s New Novel” [review of <hi>Les Miserables</hi>] published in the
                    <hi>Spectator</hi></p>
                <p><date when="18620215">Feb. 15</date><lb/><!-- double-check this date? - tm -->
                    “The Bloody Son”published as “The Fratricide,” in <hi>Once a Week</hi></p>
                <p><date when="18620426">Apr. 26</date><lb/>
                    “A Song in Time of Order” published in the <hi>Spectator</hi></p>
                    <p><date when="18620517">May 17</date><lb/>
                        “Before Parting” published in the <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18620524">May 24</date><lb/>
                        “After Death” published in the <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18620531">May 31</date><lb/>
                        “Faustine” published in the <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18620621">June 21</date><lb/>
                        “<emph>Les Miserables</emph>. Part II and III” published in the <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18620628">June 28</date><lb/>
                        “A Song in time of Revolution — 1860” published in the <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18620726">July 26</date><lb/>
                        “The Sundew” published in the <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18620816">Aug. 16</date><lb/>
                        “<emph>Les Miserables</emph>. Part IV and IV” published in the <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18620906">Sept. 6</date><lb/>
                        “August” and a review of Baudelaire’s <emph>Les Fleurs du Mal</emph> published in the
                        <emph>Spectator</emph></p>
            </div>
                <div><head><date when="18640000">1864</date></head>
                    <p><emph>The Pilgrimage of Pleasure</emph>, a verse morality-play, published anonymously in Mary
                        Gordon’s novel, <emph>The Children of the Chapel</emph></p></div>
                <div><head>1865</head>
                    <p><date when="18650000">1865</date><lb/>
                        “Gentle Spring” and “Before the Mirror” (accompanying Whistler’s picture, “The Little
                        White Girl”) published in the <emph>Catalogue of the Royal Academy Exhibition</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18650300">March</date><lb/>
                        publication of <emph>Atalanta in Calydon</emph> by Edward Moxon and Co.</p>
                    <p><date when="18650700">July</date><lb/>
                        great success of <emph>Atalanta</emph> requires second edition</p>
                    <p><date when="18651100">November</date><lb/>
                        publication of <emph>Chastelard</emph>, the first in the Mary Stuart Trilogy,
                        by Edward Moxon and Co.</p>
            </div>
                <div><head>1866</head>
                <p><date when="18660200">February</date><lb/>
                    <emph>A Selection from the Works of Lord Byron</emph>, with a preface, published by
                    Edward Moxon and Co.</p>
                    <p><date when="18660000">Spring</date><lb/>
                        <emph>Poems and Ballads</emph> printed by Moxon and Co. (<emph>MU</emph>) Swinburne orders
                        several corrections, made by hand and with the use of cancel leaves (<emph>MC</emph>). <emph>Laus Veneris: and Other Poems and Ballads</emph> (<emph>NY</emph>) published in America by Carleton and Co. This partly-pirated edition set from uncorrected Moxon proofs (<emph>MU</emph>).</p>
                    <p><date when="18660725">July 25</date><lb/>
                        <emph>Poems and Ballads</emph> (<emph>MC</emph>) published by Edward Moxon and Co. The
                        volume immediately begins to receive negative reviews.</p>
                    <p><date when="18660810">August 10</date><lb/>
                        <emph>Poems and Ballads</emph> withdrawn from publication by Moxon.</p>
                    <p><date when="18660900">September</date><lb/>
                        John Hotten re-issues <emph>Poems and Ballads</emph> using Moxon’s remaining stock
                        (<emph>HM</emph>). “Cleopatra” published in the <emph>Cornhill Magazine</emph></p>
                    <p><date when="18661000">October</date><lb/>
                        William Michael Rossetti’s defense, <emph>Swinburne’s Poems and Ballads: A
                            Criticism</emph>, published by Hotten. Swinburne’s <emph>Notes on Poems and Reviews</emph> published by
                        Hotten</p>
                    <p><date when="18661103">November 3</date><lb/>
                        Carleton publishes an American edition (<emph>NY</emph>) set from faulty Moxon
                        Uncorrected (<emph>MU</emph>) proofs.</p>
                    <p><date when="18661124">November 24</date><lb/>
                        Hotten runs out of Moxon remainders and issues a reprint of Poems and
                        Ballads (<emph>HR</emph>). Further editions in 1868, 1871, and 1873 (both by Hotten and Chatto. Chatto and Windus’ <emph>Complete Swinburne</emph> appears in 1904.)</p>
                    </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text></TEI>